good evening no I'm super low it's on but it's low my volume good evening everyone hello thank you for being here I now call to order this August 12 2025 meeting of Lancaster City Council a couple of reminders for everyone just here at the top of the meeting this meeting and its participants thank you are being recorded this evening please take a moment to silence your phones and devices if you haven't done so already first a note to bill 5 under item C on the agenda was not taken up by the Public Safety Committee last evening it was placed on this agenda due to advertising requirements but since it was not advanced to full council we will not do a first reading this evening during our meeting this evening there will be opportunities for public comment the first general public comment period is for residents that registered in advance to speak about items that are not on the agenda residents may also comment on individual items on our legislative agenda to section 9 finally a second public comment period will be at the end of the agenda for any other speakers wishing to address council all speakers will please be reminded to begin with your name and block of residence or municipality if not in the city for the meeting record be advised that public comment is not a question and answer period all comments are limited to three minutes per speaker to help us keep time this evening I have the light in front of me here it will turn green when a speaker's time begins it will blink yellow when there is one minute remaining and begin to blink red when three minutes has been reached if a speaker continues past three minutes I will ask them to end their comment I appreciate everyone's cooperation to maintain equal time and also order during this meeting speakers addressing City Council members of the audience are all expected to conduct themselves in an orderly manner and please remain respectful to others now for all of those who are willing and able please rise for the Pledge of Allegiance mr. Harris would you please call the roll of
members yes madam president mr. Menn here mr. Arroyo here mr. Cleese here miss Craig here miss Diaz here mr. Hirsch here and president Begay here we
will now move to the approval or minutes of the August 11th last evening's meeting of committees of Council motion to approve second we have a motion and a second for the meeting minutes councillors any comments on the minutes
like to thank mr. Harris for turning them around thank you very much I
changed that in my notes because I was thinking we were working on yesterday's meeting but that's not the case because that was committees I'm going to withdraw my request for a motion and start again uh we're moving to the approval of the July 22nd regular meeting of council minutes motion to approve second thank you we do have a motion and a second councillors any comments on the minutes from the July 22nd meeting
hearing none Mr. Harris Mr. Mapp aye Mr. Arroyo aye Mr. Cleese aye Ms. Craig aye Ms. Diaz aye Mr.
Mr. Hirsch aye and President Bacon aye thank you as always for keeping me straight Mr. Harris our next item on the agenda this evening is proclamations honors awards and resolutions of recognition I don't believe we haven't have any this evening is that the case Mr. Harris that is the case thank you so much that will then take us to our first public comment period again this is reserved for residents who have contacted the city clerk prior to the cutoff before the meeting to request the opportunity to address counsel quick reminders just said this I'll say it again we're my limit comments are limited to three minutes per speaker please be mindful of equal time and please begin with your name and block of residence or your municipality for the case of non-city residents mr. Harris has provided a list of speakers that is on the screen before us this evening to help continue to move things along so this is the order in which they were submitted speakers will come to the microphone that's located over to your left my right and so if you'd like to pre line up that would help us make sure that things keep moving so our first speaker this evening mr. Harris is Darrell legacy thank you mr. legacy are you here this evening I did not happen to see him our next speaker mr. Harris is John tell Toland mr. Toland and as you're coming to the microphone right over here as the first speaker you may need to flip it on the little on off
toggle to on thank you yeah it was already on uh jontel tolan first and only block of 68 wise av i guess i'll start off by talking about last meeting um i'm appalled and insulted by the way we were gaslit at last council meeting i held what i wanted to say so that i could do some digging so that i could think about why you chose to regurgitate a script that was given to you by the very people who seek to cause us harm when you serve us don't you think asking them questions at the least and being transparent about what you discuss with them what questions you actually asked would be sound instead of trying to quell what you think is a mob from the start of the meeting when really it's just concerned citizens of what you serve coming to you with questions information to share an overall constructive dialogue I left angry because I was I left early because I was angry the more I look into what AI data centers do to society in general not even just environmental effects it brings up anger fear sorrow anguish I want our kids to have a future don't you part of your job is to work with us there are people who came to the last meeting with very valuable information and I hope you took it upon yourselves to look into any and everything you could from last meeting to now can you tell us about any independent third party environmental impact studies that were completed for this project and where can the public access it who in our community not corporate representatives have been consulted directly about this project and where is that record will you commit to showing up to a town hall style question and answer where residents not just corporate PR teams can speak freely and have their questions answered without time limits how will you ensure air noise and heat pollution from this facility will not harm our neighborhoods especially black and brown and low-income communities who already face environmental burdens given what happened in Memphis where a data center project disproportionately impacted black communities and ignored environmental justice concerns how will you guarantee that our city does not repeat those same mistakes who will be held personally accountable if the project harms residents or the environment if you are truly committed to making Lancaster safe and clean in reference to the Dana Center, could you put that comment in writing right now for the public record? Have you took a look at Memphis like I mentioned the last time? Have you looked at Tucson? These are just two cases with very different results. Know that we will continue fighting against this because this is our lives at stake, our futures at stake. If you represent us and yourselves, you should be alarmed and angry. You should be jumping to make moves to fight this given what's happening in the country. When you plan new developments, do you imagine who will suffer the consequences? you do think about the consequences, right? And who suffers the most, it's not just the rich who live in Chestnut Hill with tree canopy streets, it's the families in the southeast, the black and brown kids playing near the train tracks, the elders who already can't afford their electric bills or their inhalers. Energy prices will go up and a whole new cycle of downward spiral and degradation of this community's character will begin. I wonder how many of you have already considered any of this, if both these data centers were to be built, it would not only affect the city, it would impact half a million people in the surrounding county. This is not a win as the mayor or the governor said, selling Lancaster soul to companies who will use and abuse us and throw us away when they are done why would you want to why would you want or allow something like this to go through unchecked unless you alone benefit from it in some way unless you are so naive that you would believe everything these companies say to you to be able to be swindled so easily are you not insulted or enraged
thank you thank you Mr. Harris our next speaker please Brett Stanley good evening good evening
my name is brett stanley living in mountainville but working in lancaster at an aerospace lab adjacent to mccaskey i was born here and grew up watching the farms and fields turned into shopping centers and authorized housing developments i was too young and distracted to care to do much about that seems inevitable and out of my control i have a background in metal fabrication i don't speak very often so i was here at the first two meetings We've kind of figured out that this is like a fact-finding process. And, yeah, so in custom fabrication, the workers ourselves don't get to decide what companies we service. And I've had the privilege of seeing direct influence on my community in some ways. But I'd be saddened and unsurprised if some of the jobs created through these centers are padded with work already done locally. I'm opposed to AI data centers, and more qualified individuals have discussed negative implications at the previous two meetings. At the end of 2024, the company I used to work for in Wrightsville quadrupled their output, or had been asked to quadruple their output of data center catalysts, which they had been making for years, with the suggestion that my employer would store the catalyst long-term until needed. That was at the end of 2024. I don't know when all of this money got moved around. This leads me to believe that a knowing investor had plans to manipulate individuals to begin stockpiling with the potential knowledge that data centers would be built. If I recall correctly, these are selective catalytic reduction units. They're supposed to be good for three to five years. supposed to reduce 90 percent of emissions turning the emissions into nitrogen and water byproducts but who's going to be checking up on these companies how can we verify their you know their facts and what what is our recourse when we find out it's bad just like everywhere else has what do we do when they're expanding to water and it threatens our aquifers uh as a community we are trying to piece together the true timeline of events and how they were approved without public knowledge by the time we will have the full picture likely the damage will have been done we don't know how this was approved logically or ethically however working under these assumptions parts of these data centers likely have already been fabricated prior to our knowledge not boosting the economy potentially speculation but with all the wool that's been pulled over our eyes between even the board and what they've been told uh what we've been told uh it's just alarming that's pretty much all i have to say thank you mr samuel mr harris our next speaker
please next is alexander king mr king good evening good evening i live on the 600 block of north
shipping street and i've been reading about the data center uh projects for lancaster city with with increasing alarm in the newspaper. My, Memphis was mentioned previously, my son lives in Memphis, goes to college there, and he's been telling me some real horror stories about how data centers in the African American area of that city have been really trashing that neighborhood. One of the specific ways that happens is through the backup diesel generators, which is, of course, the most dirtiest way you can make electricity. But when the grid is overstrained, particularly in the summer, because it's also hot in Memphis, then they just need to kick in those diesel generators to have enough power for their computers. Also, for a while now, actually, I've been following the developments in Abilene, Texas, which seems to become increasingly uninhabitable from the noise. So as is reported in the newspaper, you can have water-cooled or air-cooled data centers, and apparently the ones in Lancaster are to be air-cooled, which means they will be very noisy. Inside a data center, it can be 95 decibels or higher, which is like standing next to a jet airplane. Outside the data center, you can have a loud hum 24 hours seven. And some have compared that to traffic on Highway 30, for example. But traffic on Highway 30 is pretty minimal at 2, 3, 4 a.m. And the jobs in these data centers are all actually not all that great. It's routine maintenance. There's a few skilled people, and the development history with other data centers going in in other cities, usually the most skilled people are brought in.
They're not from the community.
Whereas the community members getting jobs there are minimal skill and not so great pay in these places. And so I find it really surprising that the city planner was able to make this decision unilaterally on how to class a data center. And so I implore council to evaluate this thoroughly, look at reestablishing noise ordinances for industrial enterprises, and thinking about how data centers are something new, and therefore require a brand new classification in the zoning, and thank you.
Thank you, Mr. King. Mr. Harris, our next speaker, please.
Next is Irene Grievous.
Ms. Grievous. Good evening. irene grievous 900 block of westland avenue i'm here this evening following up from last month's july 8th regarding my property in 901 manor street and the city's continued lack of response to my repeated requests going back to 2021 for third-party inspections arbitration and a clear path to resolution for years i've been asking for a fair and neutral way to resolve this and for years nothing has happened meantime lancaster is in the middle of a major housing crisis and this property could be a home for a family right now if the city will simply work with me instead of leaving this matter in limbo people in the community have been asking me directly to rent the home just last week someone had placed a note on the back door they work in the construction field and were willing to make any necessary repairs just to live there a man named sean carter who has done work for me before and tried contacting the city for help but got nowhere and ignored and just today i was approached by a gentleman by the name of charlie bruce caskey and with his permission he's in a desperate need of housing his unit and all the surrounding units in the 200 block of west chestnut street are being covered or being converted into 250 a night bed and breakfast rentals that change alone would displace at least six families this is reality we're facing a long-term residence they are being priced out and pushed out while available homes just sit empty because the city refuses to move forward to basic inspections and mediation every week of delay means another week a home standing empty another week families looking for a place to live in another week a family fails to take action that could make a real difference in this in the people's lives i am asking again for one a prompt independent inspection for 901 manor street two arbitration and mediation to re to resolve any disputes three a timeline for resolution so a home can be restored to a residential use immediately this is not just about my property it's about housing stability for Lancaster residents you have the power to help people in our community in our community house I urge you to act now before more families are displaced it's your job this is what you were elected to to do thank you to help the residents
thank you thank you counselors uh excuse me i'll just take a just a moment to remind you that we were copied on um the follow-up from ms grievous request last month on july 16th so everyone has a copy of what that was uh mr harris our next speaker please next speaker is uh
good evening hi my name is sarah i'm from the 400 block of west frederick and like many people here i'm here to address the data center issue i spoke at the planning commission last week and mentioned that i hold a master's degree in international relations with an emphasis in sustainable development so i've studied extensively the importance of resource management and the impact this kind of digital infrastructure has on communities specifically where resources are already strained like in Lancaster the issue with the issues with the data center are many and community members have spoken to the city council about these harms and will continue tonight noise air and water pollution increases in utility costs being held politically hostage by a massive corporation the fact that core weave is a deeply unprofitable company with many billions of dollars in debt and i'm sure that more people tonight will enumerate these many harms i'll reiterate what i think is the most concerning issue which is the enormous strain on our grid on the low end with conservative estimates this data center would use quadruple the amount of energy of all the houses in lancaster city combined and i could talk about these harms extensively but i would like to focus on the next steps that we're looking for as a community last week i spoke to the planning commission among many other concerned citizens and the planning commission acted immediately with some concrete steps and while there's still a lot more we're looking to see from the planning commission they scheduled a public hearing for october 1st and engaged seriously with the possibility of a new zoning category we're here to ask for the same kind of concrete actions from our city council because it has been almost a month since this announcement was made and for the planning commission they made steps within the meeting that we came to them here are just a few examples of the type of concrete actions i'm referring to number one you could earmark the revenue from the building permits for affordable housing the eight million dollars that you've received someone mentioned at the planning commission meeting that it is easier to get an energy guzzling million square foot data center in lancaster than it is to get affordable housing if this project is inevitable use the permit revenue for the city's greatest need two another example you could put pressure on coreweave to new to use renewable energy there There are some data centers in the world that attempt to center their mission holistically around renewable energy. CoreWeave is not one of these. Their data centers in Europe use almost 100% renewable energy, but in the States, many of their data centers don't at all. So why are we not putting this pressure on them? We know they're capable of it. I'm running out of time, so I just want to reemphasize that I'm not here to spit vitriol at you. I actually do believe that many of you really, really care about this community and are working on this. here in a spirit of collaboration to share what we believe would be a specific and tangible next step from you we're really looking for action thank you thank you mr harris our next speaker
please next speaker is patricia eckman good evening i'm from this lampeter township i've been reading the articles in the lexington newspaper concerning the proposed data centers at greenfield road and harrisburg pike preliminary construction has already begun at the greenfield road site prior to this to purchasing the properties it was already approved the backhand handed zoning approval is very disturbing and sends a message to the community that obtaining a bar was more important than any inconveniences and hazards to residents i live less than a mile from the greenfield road property along 343 340 in regents park condo development and i have two main concerns with the project the health impact on the residents and the excessive use of water and electricity to run the operation the air and water quality may be compromised due to the 70 plus diesel generators and the wastewater pumped back into the waterways since i'm in close proximity to the data center i'm worried about the noise from the generators and the cooling equipment according to a news article in the august 9th 2025 lancaster newspaper a professor of environmental health sciences at university of michigan school of public health rick neitzel stated and i quote there's evidence that noise disturbance can over the long term lead to more serious health problems like high blood pressure increased risk of stroke and hearing loss the science certainly shows that it can be bad for us if we're exposed at high enough levels for long enough end of quote in the same article jeff sterla of wilson construction who is doing the work says the noise will be like the traffic noise on route 30. i live right near room 30 and i can tell you the noise at night can be very loud and i really don't want that to be doubled with this new project nidsel replies and i quote the data center may produce less noise than a highway during the day the center operates around the clock including at night when highway traffic decreases end of quote i asked the city of lancaster to put an ordinance in place to cover data centers while it may be too late though i hope not for this center unless they want to expand in the future and will put a halt to the center on harrisburg pike until the company puts in place remedies for residents concerns neitzel goes on to say that it is possible to limit noise with air-cooled equipment designed to trap the noise from getting out into the environment secondly the excessive water and electricity use is an environmental issue will nearby residents experience low water pressure who is paying for the ppl substation to be erected on the data center property will residents see major increases in their electric bills due to the excessive use of electric how will waste water be treated and disposed of and there are many other answered unanswered questions the city government does have a we've reached three minutes to provide a healthy environment thank you thank you so much mr harris our next speaker
please next speaker is nathan bishop good evening good evening my name is nathan bishop i'm a resident of the 100 block of president ave in lancaster township and i'm a renewable energy transactions attorney i'm addressing you today regarding the proposed coreweave data centers out of concern for their impact on the people and environment of lancaster these data centers will bring enormous monetary and environmental costs right now the data center plan for 216 greenfield Road will be equipped with 72 diesel backup generators. Our air quality is already the 22nd in the nation for short-term particle pollution. We need to make our air cleaner, not more polluted. Along with the new diesel generation, the power consumption of the 100 megawatt facility will be drawing from Lancaster's existing power supplies, which are composed of 33% coal-based generation, leading to a huge increase in greenhouse gas emissions. The monetary costs of data centers are already well documented. Rate payers, normal people, end up paying higher electricity prices when new data centers draw upon existing transmission and generation resources. I call the council's attention to two reports on this matter. The report titled Extracting Profits from the Public, How Utility Rate Payers are Paying for Big Tech's Power by Eliza Martin and Ari Pesco of the Harvard Law School Environmental and energy law program and the analysis of the 2025 26 rpm based residual auction prepared by the independent market manager for pjm which is the regional transmission organization servicing lancaster this report demonstrates that normal people are paying billions of dollars in higher electricity bills as a direct result of new data centers and that these costs are only expected to get worse i call upon the city to reject any further data sector applications and with respect to the center plan for 216 greenfield road to coordinate with the state public utility commission and pjm to gain access to all agreements between pjm and core weave to insist on new direct co-located solar plus storage generation paid for by core weave to service all of the electricity and backup power needs of the facility which would help bring green jobs to lancaster prevent air and climate pollution and prevent utility rate hikes and to establish proactive restrictions on the facility from switching to water cooling systems and to address the annoying concern issues thank you for your time and attention to this matter
thank you mr harris our next speaker please next is shauna yordy good evening hi i'm shauna yordy
i'm on the 800 block of third street i was here last week for the planning commission meeting and spoke about some similar things and i heard a lot of people who were numbers people and who who are facts people and I talked about how I'm a feelings person that's what I have to give and as a feelings person there's a lot of big scary stuff that's going on in the world right now and I often find myself wondering what I can do and the only thing that I come up with is that we should all be wailing in the streets right now that's the thing that makes the most sense to me but nobody else is doing that yet so instead I make art and I hang out with kids and right now I'm hanging out with some kids who are four to eight years old and we're building a world we're building an art installation where we're looking at different perspectives we've got a town and a mountain and some water in the underground and when we're building this world we talk about our roles and we talk about the impact of our actions and how what we do in the town affects the mountain and how what happens on the mountain affects the salmon that we put into our river and there's different kinds of people right there's number people and there's feelings people and there's kids and there's power people and right now it seems to me that you guys are the power people and the power people need to take some ideas from these kids who come up with these incredible ideas they have all of these out of the box solutions because they're not bound by silly rules and ideas of like well somebody said that there was an ordinance that we have to do xyz and there's a law about the ha ha ha ha ha ha there's people in power who can change that stuff and come up with innovative ideas and new ideas just like the kids can decide that they don't want a data center in our town because what's going to happen to the animals that live on the mountain and how are we going to breathe and how are we going to drink the water and how are the duck's going to stay upright on the pond that we built when none of us can breathe we're going to have a public health crisis on our hands and i hear a lot of people talking about um boosting the power grid because it's going to take all of this power and such and such and such and what i wonder is what actions can be taken to boost the public health system in lancaster city to deal with the effects that's going to happen when the chronically ill people and the people with asthma and the people with migraines and the people who are on inhalers can't breathe and what's going to happen when our kids can't breathe the kids can't eat the dollars they can't breathe the dollars they can't drink the dollars they don't give a shit about the dollars they just want to breathe and so at that time maybe like is that what happens is that we don't do anything now and then the kids can't breathe and then we're all wailing in the streets because it's all that we have left and all we can do is just be feelings people crying in the streets what are you going do so we don't get to that place what's going to happen how do we keep from getting there thank you
thank you mr harris our next speaker please next speaker is gerald griner is gerald griner here
our next speaker mr harris is dan weigel good evening uh dan weigel uh clarendon drive um as you may have noticed there's a petition going around um there's a petition going around in our community about the data center we have hundreds of signatures on it it's been in the news obviously this is a big deal to our community I'd like to take my time tonight first to read the petition to you all as AI companies to send on Pennsylvania to build data centers local governments need to make a choice stand up to big tech or sell out their constituents in Lancaster City we're facing the construction of two AI data centers that have gone under the radar until recently setting aside the negative effects of the global AI race these data centers will cause price hikes for utilities lower the supply of water and electricity and create harmful new air and noise pollution across the country many communities that have become sites for data centers have been forced to deal with rolling blackouts and low water pressure or watching their utility bills become more and more expensive we don't want that to happen in Lancaster City we call on Lancaster City government to do the following one City Council must request from the Planning Commission an ordinance that covers the zoning of data centers and rescind the zoning officers decision to
zone the Harrisburg Pike and Greenfield Road data centers as wholesale trade
and storage they are not warehouses to mayor Sirachi and City Council must work with the public to pass a plan that insulates Lancaster residents from the negative effects of data centers for example price hikes for utilities low water pressure and rolling blackouts three city government must act with complete transparency and not issue any further permits to data centers until these changes have been made finally we call on Lancaster City to be a leader in Pennsylvania and stand up for working people like you all over the interests of big tech companies now I'd like to pull the room of those in the room tonight many of you i believe have signed the petition for those who have not who have heard of it for the first time i'd like a show of hands how many of you are with us in our demands and
stand with us for the record nearly everyone please keep your hands raised for a moment
to you sitting up front i turn the question on you do you hear us and are you with us please raise your hands a bit higher please everyone on city council mayor sirachi do you hear us
are you with us this is a conversation that i want to continue to have because there are some of the things that you're demanding that i can't i can't respond to most especially around the public utility commission and the regulation of electricity and so i i hear you on the air quality water use utilization which this facility will use less water than its previous use which is lsc communications which is one of our top 10 water customers noise independently evaluated so what i can say is that i am hearing you council is hearing you we're having conversations about all of the things that you're asking for but there are some things that are outside and beyond the capacity of the body to respond to most especially energy regulation pjm puc and how ppl is responding to questions about rate hikes rolling blackouts etc we cannot answer those questions thank you
mr greiner i also uh i echo that sentiment i do have some uh responses after the end of public comment to that effect but i do appreciate comments i do hear you and i know that many members of council have shared your concerns we've spoken to me spoken to the administration
and members of the city government thank you i look forward to your actions counselor craig
thank you council president um i am very interested in everything that everyone has to say but it's really difficult when someone's at the speaker and and i know you want to applaud them because what they're saying is good but if we can't hear them you know then i'm getting half half of what they're saying so can we click instead of clap
Fair. Thank you, Council Craig. Mr. Harris, our next speaker.
Our next speaker is Jo Ellen Wisnowski.
Good evening. Good evening, everyone. Thank you.
Thank you all for being here, especially our council and mayor, and for all your service to our community. We appreciate everything you do and for being here. I also appreciate my fellow community members. p.s i'm in the 200 block of north pine street and i own a business here in lancaster city 100 block of chestnut so i uh respect what everyone is having to say here and appreciate all the amazing data what i have a specific question on is that the city of lancaster voted last november to be part of home rule which was most most uh was pushed forward and and discussed and paid for to discuss how that was going to be implemented with the city did vote yes to it i'm writing what i haven't seen anything updated on the city of lancaster website as to how we as citizens can implement our right to petition ordinances i'm not even sure if this was an ordinance passed but i'm looking at article 7 ordinances which says general proposals increases requirements for public notice prior to adoption and article 11 adds citizen ability to petition to propose reconsider or appeal an ordinance by referendum I'd like to know how our council members and our governance here are actually if this is an ordinance that was passed why the public wasn't allowed the petitioning that was guaranteed by us passing home rule which again I haven't seen any updates since all the things have been put on the website as to how our people can use our government that we passed to actually be a participant in these situations which do affect every single person who lives and works in this city and i leave all these wonderful people who have done amazing research to give all the details but that's something i specifically want addressed to our community and you know we had letters coming out saying yes please vote for home rule here's what it's going to do for us now how can we as people who have milked hundreds here have been coming to these events and represent only a portion but how do we get the word out to the rest of our community how they can be involved as well in the governing of our city
thank you thank you ms mosnowski to um to address that very specific question i do think it's important to mention that this was not an ordinance that was brought forward to council because of the processes that the owner of the property chose to take it did not come before any body of the city administration board commission or authority thank you appreciate that mr harris the next
speaker please our next speaker is jennifer siegel good evening hi my name is jennifer siegel but everyone here knows me as coral rights i live in marietta but i host events here in lancaster city and rely on people's willingness to travel to lancaster to pay my bills and most of my favorite people live here but more than that we all breathe the air and whether or not i can is dictated by you all doing your job as city council members this data center is bigger than just lancaster city at the last or at the last meeting there was some opaqueness around what carissa technology technology technology technology parks overall plans were for the other property it's as clear as day on carissa's website that their intentions are for the lots that they've purchased for data centers across two sites they are already advertising it to their clients but what you did make clear last council meeting was that no permits for the other site have been filed we need to move while we still have options at the planning meeting last week it was determined that not only can you create an appropriate ordinance for future data centers but also for the one that you implied couldn't that you could interrupt the process of because you haven't made any moves since last council meeting I'm assuming you're either getting something for rolling over and playing dead or you've got the most severe case of people pleasing I have ever seen except who are you pleasing because none of us are pleased people pleasing only ever hurts people and enables bad behavior in this case in corporations AI isn't going away data centers aren't going to get kinder and better managed we are at the very beginning of a technological revolution and right here right now you all get to decide if it's going to be in favor of the people or the corporations and I believe that each and every one of you has the integrity inside of you to choose the people and if you decide to roll over and play dead then you better know that protests will be regular occurrences that you all will have to contend with please be brave start the ordinance work now we can be a positive example for the country but if you refuse then know that everyone in this county will know that every single one of you including the mayor is a coward and that you are to blame for the technocratic takeover of Lancaster Pennsylvania everyone will know that you are the reason they can't afford their electricity that you are the reason they can't hear themselves think you are the reason their home depreciated significantly you are the reason the visitor stopped visiting and spending money in our city you are the reason that people can't breathe I suspect some of you never thought that you would be managing more than standard things but this is the reality this is what you signed up for this is bigger than Lancaster City it's bigger than Lancaster County if you can't handle that pressure then you shouldn't be in government if you can't handle showing up for people in this then there is no way we can count on you to push back when ice arrives they're already in the area everything is connected and impacts everything else we all breathe the same air for the sake of all of us rise up thank you thank you Mr. Harris our next
speaker please next speaker is Samuel Pollack good evening hello it's Samuel Pollack from a hundred block of Euclid Avenue behind Regal Cinemas thanks everybody for coming out I'm here to speak about two things it's gonna be the data center and I think the civilian police review board I saw was later on the agenda I'll try to keep it quick people pretty much I think I've got some why these data centers are so horrifying and terrible live in Lancaster for a long time one of my favorite things to do here is hiking around the county you know Lancaster Conservancy you got all those cool was some very close Lancaster City actually wind off landing the wing stem is starting to go off right now I think the problem is like we keep having like I'm like a feelings person too I'm also worried about climate change because reality is it's simply not a hoax it's true in fact when it's happening to the pollinators it's happening there climate change is very very real and i worry that like when we bring up like concerns like oh don't worry like we're gonna get the great grape when all this new electricity comes so it'll be able to handle it but it's like wasn't that part of the problem though because fossil fuels do electricity and that's what's destroying us here locally too so it's like that doesn't really make me feel better if the factual basis is still there that makes any sense and the other thing is i we talked about like renewables for these things you know i saw i've also read you know some of these companies talking about oh we want these net supposedly like uh net zero ai data centers but even these ones in europe they're using some fossil fuels at the end of the day even the best ones in finland use like five percent and that's only like best case scenario the reality is if you look this up nobody really knows how much these are going to use in the future in fact all we know is that they're exponentially increasing and the only thing that can keep that around the clock is fossil fuels to to do that for when it's the big thing in fact that's the whole thing facts don't care about your feelings fossil fuels will be the only thing that will be able to power these increasing amounts literally you can't do this without fossil fuels i.e this contributes to climate change i.e this is destroying our planet that is although that's global it's also local it's happening right here at the conservancies that we all enjoy it's happening everywhere and the civilian police review board it's it may seem different but in some ways it's the same like you're telling us to feel better like we're gonna do this civilian police review board and I thought the whole thing would be an advisory joke frankly when I looked at it but at least I thought it'd be something but then I was so disappointed to see that half of its police officers they're like current police officers that like the Lancaster State Police Chief is on that review board and then you you don't not just pass law enforcement officers you're the mayor is going to be appointing current law enforcement officers and that's not the case in other civilian like that's not the case with uh New York's as I said that's not a case with what did like Martinsburg West Virginia you know there they are actually civilians are appointed there are you can't even be a past law enforcement officer for some of those review boards in New York City you can't even have been in law enforcement or public any of those types of things period here we're talking about the police investigating themselves how the heck does that work literally the police are the civilian review board that's not civilian review board that's a police review board I'm sorry that's that's all
I gotta say mr. Harris our next speaker please next speaker is Christine good evening you can feel free to bring that down a little lower should we're not I hope that's not as low as it goes there we go okay perfect thank you my
name is Christine Kennedy I live in the first block of Market Street in Lancaster Pennsylvania and I come today to tell a little bit about what I've learned and where I was wrong with some of the comments I made at the prior City council meeting some of those were I've learned that data centers are not necessarily Bitcoin which was the Bitcoin mining experience that I had been near and deafened by that indoor data centers are very different than outdoor Bitcoin mining center that I experienced and that fans and water are not the only alternatives for cooling at a data center and that core weave has committed to starting in 2025 that all their new data centers will incorporate liquid cooling capabilities i questioned what liquid cooling capabilities would include and according to wikipedia liquid cooling fluids can use water and liquid dialectic fluids of which wikipedia has a huge list of what that could include i was glad to see that the city of lancaster is looking to to engage a consultant with knowledge and experience with immediate and long-term considerations and mitigation options of data center construction operation and, for example, what potential hazards may be associated with any spills of liquid dialectics. I believe that corporations purchasing land and developing data centers are moving more rapidly than local municipalities are prepared for, similar in many ways to the explosion of the internet my hope is that we can educate our elected officials municipal employees and residents with good information and quickly learn as best we can from the experience of other municipalities among my questions now is how might we be an example to other communities that as we're playing catch up with this train that's running so fast how might we be able to do what we can when we can. To do, for example, what Sarah Etterhanosa recommended and Nathan Bishop and Dan Weigel. I'm very impressed with the kind of research and the resources that we have right here in Lancaster. And I was proud of our city becoming an example to small cities across the country of having a comprehensive plan that incorporates references to all ages, not just certain ages, and all people. We can be an example, too, of fighting the fight to catch up and do the best we can, and maybe even make us a community that Corweave might wanna point to because they've done the best they really can to help us. Thank you.
Thank you. Mr. Harris, our next speaker, please.
next is i'm sorry lindsay fitting good evening hello my name is lindsay fitting i live on the
500 block of west james street and i'm here to talk about you guessed it the ai data centers so as a resident of lancaster city i fear for our access to water and electricity if this data center is built we already have so much evidence of ai data centers causing droughts such as in Texas where all their data centers combined are projected to use 50 billion gallons of water this year. Residents who are trying to just drink water, shower, and water their plants are being told to conserve their water for the sake of these data centers. Doesn't this sound reminiscent of every other environmental disaster caused by huge corporations? Somehow the solution is always that we need to take shorter showers. Air cooling has been touted as a solution to water shortages However, this is not an option because CoreWeave proudly states on their website that liquid cooling is essential for large-scale AI performance. There are other ways regular citizens will have to pay to accommodate AI. My friend in Illinois now pays $200 a month for electricity in his one-bedroom apartment. His boss pays $600 per month for his house because their electric company, ComEd, passes the cost of electricity to all of its customers to keep up with demand created by AI data centers. for comparison my electric bill in lancaster for a one bedroom has been 30 to 40 dollars per month since 2022 and so was his in chicago the ceo of core weave claims the lancaster data center will drive economic growth but for who himself and his shareholders not the single parent trying to make sure their children have water to drink and bathe not the 20 something year old server working doubles to barely afford their one red bedroom apartment and not the first time home buyer getting ready to pay more bills than they ever have in their life i don't care that you made a silly picture of your dog seemingly out of nowhere i don't care that you think chat gbt is a substitute for a therapist and i don't care that ai wrote your essay so you can graduate and not have to think about these things that you were supposed to be learning i speak for all lancaster county residents when i say we will be paying for these ai data centers with our quality of life and wallets if we do not stop it thank you thank you mr harris our next speaker please next speaker is
reagan layman good evening um my name is reagan layman and i live on the 500 block of north shippen street and i appreciate the council giving us an opportunity today to speak on the issues that are pressing our city since the last city council meeting i noticed that the city has published an faq on ai data centers on their website and while my three minutes doesn't allow me to address each point i'd like to address some of the statements on the web page in response to this data impacts on air quality i understand that the pa department environmental protection is reviewing the permit on backup diesel generators for these ai data centers however this doesn't address the larger picture that the fact that we're seeing across the nation we're restarting coal plants in order to fuel these ai generate ai data centers not to mention we're now seeing through mile island is being restarted to power a microsoft ai data center as well so in the end we're impacting the air quality of not just lancaster but of all pennsylvanians additionally are we supposed to simply trust that these diesel generators will only be run as backup power are we going to have to depend on self-reporting from these ai data centers how are we going to enforce that these permits are being followed and won't change in the future secondly when it comes to noise pollution we're developing on the developer to self-assess the noise impact of course if they're self-reporting i would assume that they're motivated to report as neutral they want to finish this project they want to make money You also state that the city will be reviewing the study. But given that this administration seems to be already biased towards these data centers, this whole FAQ page seems very pro-data center, I have a difficult time trusting that assessment. Once again, I ask, what are the means of enforcement if these AI data centers end up contributing to noise pollution? These companies don't care about us. They only care about profit. Most fines are a slap on the wrist to a billion-dollar company. Will we be tied up in endless litigation if we pursue legal recourse? while i understand that the mayor is pursuing a community benefits agreement with the data centers my understanding is that municipal zoning ordinances are easier to enforce than cbas so why wouldn't we start setting these protections these zoning protections in place now during a time when our clean air and water protections are being stripped away at the federal level we can't afford any complacency on the state and municipal level if we're going to protect our neighbors despite the public turnout i've seen at two different meetings so far despite the thousands of emails that I know that you have received. When I checked the agenda earlier today, I didn't see anything about the data centers, and I'm really disappointed. I'm asking that the council today to amend the agenda to take action and start this rezoning process. Data centers are not warehouses. They should have never been categorized as warehouses and skipped a planning commission meeting. Let's take steps now to protect our communities before it's too late. Thank you, I yield my time.
Thank you.
Mr. Harris, our next speaker.
Next speaker is Frank Arcoglio. Good evening. Arcoglio. Frank Arcoglio, Old Trinity Place. So at the last council meeting, I asked the great Watergate question, which is, what did you know, and when did you know it? Well, I think I've got some answers. The planning commission had no idea. They had to read it in the newspaper. The city council, according to council president, said, and I quote, we were made aware of this not terribly long ago. It's new information for many of us. so then who knew well I think there's only one body after that I think it's the administration the we first found out about it in February with a nice LNP article announcing the project and quoting the mayor is saying she was excited to support the transit transformation it was a great win-win for Lancaster no mention of zoning process no mention of anything having to do with what needs to be done in order to make it a reality in July we finally get an another LNP article public input may be limited how about non-existent what how is this possible well the mystery was cleared up at the zoning board meeting by Betsy Logan the bureau chief of planning the truth is that the developer got letters from the city approving the zoning before the property was even purchased long before february 19th touting how wonderful it is they had already approved the thing isn't that great the city must have been either in negotiations or reviewing whatever was sent to them for months but guess what they kept it quiet and the approval was based on bogus zoning as wholesale trade and storage in other words a warehouse in order to avoid any scrutiny and now we stand here being told it's too late to do anything how how deceitful how underhanded that is authoritarian behavior and we believe me we know what authoritarian behavior is because we see it every day in dc i called it and i have called it zoning fraud and i think that that zoning determination needs to be rescinded and be rescinded now thank you mr
harris our next speaker please our last speaker is tony dastra good evening it's an evening
uh tony dash's 700 block in new holland avenue so what i signed up to talk about was actually parking um but i'm going to connect these two issues because you have some issues that web out over time the city has a parking issue it depends on how you look at it in what perspective that issue is maybe the city is implementing positive changes for safety and it's taking away your perceived parking so you now feel left out maybe the city isn't doing enough about the parking situation maybe you feel like your parking isn't protected you need a residential zone there are wicked problems in our community that have gone poorly addressed for decades this really isn't solely on you guys this is councils before you administrations before you but right now we're looking at a problem with the data center i won't belabor details because i've said a lot about it i had feelings at the planning commission meeting but we're looking at one big issue that the public is looking for y'all to act on to say something on and i understand that you may need to ask questions of professional advice on what you can and can't do but it has been a month you're kind of speaking volumes by not saying much at all i agree with a lot of the the sentiments in this room um i'm very disappointed in this government i appreciate to the prior comments because unfortunately we want to demonstrate that we can have a good local government why because the top needs to mirror the bottom and right now unfortunately the behaviors of not just this body but bodies across this country are mirroring the top it's the marketing is better we have a comprehensive plan that still i here we finally put the rfp out for but y'all really need to ask the planning commission to act on this and y'all need to do something yourselves as well you need to speak out you need to people need to see that you're aligned in the regulation of this development because the damage it can do will affect us for generations to come much like the issue of parking has thank you there were two speakers that were not present when
when their names were called. I'm gonna call them in the order which they were on the list. Darryl Lagasse. That's me. Yes.
Good evening. Thank you, sorry. I came here directly from a meeting with my family about end-of-life care for my father, so I hope that that shows how important this is to me. I'm very sorry to hear that,
and then may I also have you start
with your block of residence? Thank you, oh, I'm sorry. So I'm in the 100 block of North Main. Thank you. So I have a couple points, a couple questions, and a charge to the council. So first, I wanna say that for those of us that were here I think it was maybe two city council meetings ago we heard the budget and all of the information about where our money is being spent you may have remembered that the storm the wastewater treatment plant had to purchase a quote-unquote sliver of land from PPL and that required a land development plan so we who own the wastewater treatment plant we're doing a land development plan to ourselves the city and yet the AI data center now they don't need one we don't have to worry about them doing one we'll just trust them. That is ludicrous. That is preposterous. Two, I am very concerned with the fact that the governor and the mayor are both so gung-ho about this. And frankly, the mayor, I understand that you have said there's little we can do. There are restrictions in place. There are things that we can't undo. What you could do is speak out. You could say, we are not welcome here. We can't stop you, but you're not welcome here. You could say, Lancaster is closed for business for AI data centers in the future. It's not that hard. So your sort of cavalier and frankly dismissive attitude tonight makes me think that you are fully full-throated in behavior in in favor of these. So here are some questions. Who is going to be responsible for checking to make sure that these data centers do not go one inch outside of the current footprint which would then of course trigger all sorts of oversight? Two, who is going to be responsible for making sure that these diesel generators are only operated as testing during the day as the requirement says three who's gonna make sure that those generators do not operate for more than 100 hours per month as the agreement says for who's gonna make sure that they never switch to water cooling down the line after we have let them come in and we say oh well they're already here we don't really have anything we can do about it so here's my charge to everybody on City Council and actually Councillor Arroyo specifically this is your chance to distance yourself from some of the mayor's policies you are running for mayor this fall you are probably going to win and this is your chance to say no this is different the mayor has decided she's for this she doesn't care this is your chance to be different the rest of the council we've been told over and over that there's nothing we can do the regulation is what it is there's two things about that one I would really like to know what communication happened between the mayor and the zoning officer when this decision was made I don't believe that he just saw this and said, oh, sounds like a warehouse to me, and just passed this. That seems ridiculous. So all of these things that we can't undo, we're not allowed to change things retroactively. We have a city councilor, or a solicitor. Let's start gumming up the works. If they can use loopholes to call a data center a warehouse, we can use loopholes to make it hard for them to get equipment in. We can use loopholes to make it hard for them to get construction equipment in. There are all sorts of things that we could do, and the fact that we're not even trying these things speaks volumes.
Thank you, Mr. Levine. there was one additional speaker who wasn't present when their name was called that was gerald weiner so i'd like to give them the opportunity uh if they are present to speak and if not i believe that's our final commenter for this period mr house is that correct thank you very much i want to thank all of our speakers and everyone who's coming here tonight i want to reiterate again that i and many members of council do share some of the same concerns as you shared this evening i want to ensure you that the city is working on independent reviews of noise studies and all manner of environmental impacts that are within our power to control and i'm advocating for updates and modernization of our noise ordinance that addresses the findings these things are really really important to get right and in my experience in government that can take more time than i wish and we all wish that they would but we're also working to get answers from our utility providers and state level entities for things like electricity usage uh rates and more that are out of city government control i want to be really clear that we don't set electricity rates we don't have a seat at the table unfortunately when it comes to that but we've been working to get answers i'm committed to keeping the public informed about updates as more become available through that faq page and also through our regular our council meetings so i do thank you all for being here that concludes our first public comment period for this evening we do have our additional agenda if anyone wishes to excuse themselves for the rest of the agenda that's okay and now would be the time to do that we will move on to the next item on our agenda there's reports requested by council confirming mr harris that we don't have any of those this evening is that correct we do not matter president thank you the next item on our agenda is reports of committees of council meetings those were held yesterday on august 11 2025. i'll give us just a moment for left books to clear our first is public safety committee councilor diaz thank you councilor diaz uh public works committee councilor hirsch
thank you council president the public works committee did meet we had one agenda item resolution 54 which is authorizing an agreement with the lancaster county conservation district which appears later on our agenda this evening that concludes the public works report of the
the public works committee thank you economic development committee councillor med uh thank
you council president the economic development committee did not meet thank you finance committee
councillor arroyo thank you council president the finance committee meeting did or i'm sorry the finance committee did meet we had one item on the on the agenda we heard from director of administrative services tina campbell yesterday for the 2025 mid-year budget report overall the city's finances are on pace as budgeted budgeted revenue is slightly ahead and budgeted expenses are below where they are expected to be at this point this is mostly due to current staff vacancies which are temporary and are looking to be filled this year that concludes my uh report and uh for
the committee thank you very much community planning committee council craig thank you
council president community planning did meet we had one item on the agenda that's administration resolution number 55 2025 granting a projection easement for lancaster parking authority thank
you very much and personnel committee councillor cleekst thank you council president the personal
committee met last evening august 11 and reviewed the appointments to the downtown investment district already and a board of plumbing examiners and the committee also reviewed re-appointments to the sign commission public art advisory board higher education authority and the board of plumbing examiners i complete my report thank you very much councillor cleeks
that takes us into our legislative agenda this evening we will begin with no nominations for appointment so i'll turn it back over to council cleeks thank you council president
MADAM PRESIDENT, I MAKE A MOTION TO APPOINT KATIE SCHIFFLET TO THE DOWNTOWN INVESTMENT DISTRICT AUTHORITY FOR A TERM FROM AUGUST 12, 2025 TO DECEMBER 31, 2029. MASON SAUDER TO THE BOARD OF PLUMBING EXAMINERS FOR A TERM FROM SEPTEMBER 12, 2025 TO SEPTEMBER 12 2026 and we appoint molly kirkhoff to the sign commission for a term from august 31st to 2025 to august 31st 2028 see sava hong binton barry corn hoser and rachel fennig hills to the public are the advisory board for the term for terms from july 31st 2025 to july 31st to 2027. jean wigglers to the higher education authority for a term from january 1st 2025 to january 1st 2030 and eric weiss barry solder sean way and trent myers to the board of plumbing examiners for terms from september 12 2025 to september 12 2026. motion to approve second we have a motion
excuse me in a second for our nominations for appointment and reappointment this evening counselors any comments on the appointments or reappointments from the public hearing Hearing none, Mr. Harris.
Mr. Medd. Aye. Mr. Arroyo. Aye. Mr. Ruiz. Aye. Ms. Gregg. Aye. Ms. Diaz. Aye.
Mr. Hirsch. Aye. And President Baker. Aye. And we thank those members of our community for their volunteer service. Next item on the agenda, item B, is Historic District. Mr. Harris, if you're ready. Yes, Madam President.
Consider the following application and recommendation from the Historical Architectural Review Board from the historical architectural review board for an improvement to a property within the historic district uh jeff baldman owner of 134 north mary street requests installation of an exterior spiral staircase on a second story rear porch and that application was recommended for approval by the historical architectural review board motion to approve second we have a motion and a second
for the historic district items counselor craig do you have any notes on these to add i don't counselors we received notes on the application and recommended and this was recommended for approval by the historical architecture review board i'll ask if there's any applicants or members of the review board that are present that have anything additional to add hearing none any additional council comments on the approvals from the public on the project
hearing none mr harris mr medd aye mr arroyo aye mr cleese aye miss craig aye
miss diaz aye mr hirsch aye president bacon aye as we mentioned earlier item c on our agenda was not taken up by the public safety committee last evening so we move to item d on our agenda which is resolutions we have resolution number 50 2025 mr harris a resolution of the city council of the
city of lancaster authorizing the proper officials of the city of lancaster to enter into an agreement to enter into a ground lease with partners for environmental stewardship and to take any and all actions to consummate the transactions contemplated by the agreement motion to
approve second second we have a motion and a second counselor craig this is coming up for
community planning thank you council president um we reviewed this in committee um a few weeks ago and it was brought forth to today administration resolution 50 2025 authorizing a grant authorizing a ground lease agreement for a sunnyside environmental center we were presented by our solicitor mr haenliger provided information on a two-part action an agreement to enter into a ground lease and a ground lease and a ground lease this will be a lengthy process for partners for environmental stewardship to design an environmental center on nine on the peninsula and then seek permits to construct the center the ground lease provides them with a 99 year lease on the property to construct and develop the center the city will continue to own the nearly nine acre tract where the environmental center will be located the agreement to enter into the lease will will govern the structure of the city's response response relationship with partners for environmental stewardship until the project definitely moves forward then the lease agreement will be signed all all costs for the project will be borne by partners with for environmental stewardship the city will have responsibilities related to the preserve surrounding the center and those are the notes that i've taken that
involved the sunny side thank you very much counselor craig i know we have uh director delphs coming uh to to address us this evening i want to thank you for being here in addition to your notes i would also add i think i recall that there was a lot of work done about community benefit for this environmental center and insurance that it would uh benefit the community directly adjacent to the sunnyside peninsula director dells if you're in your comments tonight if you could also ensure to address that as well lights on that looks good you might have to get a little closer
to it but otherwise okay good evening council is that okay yeah that's perfect thank you uh very good and uh thank you councillor craig and president baquet for the questions i'm so pleased to be here to talk about this action and this project here tonight as you know this has been a long time in the making and if you'll bear with me I just want to go over some context related to the project I know it will be a recap for many of you here tonight but I did want to just take a few moments to talk about how we got here and also if there's anybody new in the audience listening I it's good to have the background as well um i will try to keep it brief though i know we have a long night here as many of you know in october of 2023 the city adopted completed and adopted its first comprehensive plan in 30 years one of the big ideas in the comp plan entitled our future lancaster was to enhance community access to the conestoga river in order to help launch this vision the comp plan called for a nature and recreation preserve at the north end of the sunnyside peninsula and have that that preserve anchored by an environmental center city staff issued a request for proposals in november of 2023 and then later issued a conditional award to the partners for environmental stewardship in January of 2024 so it's been a little while since 2024 January 2024 since that time the solicitor's office and our outside counsel have negotiated a series of agreements with PES and the resolution before you tonight is really the culmination of that series of work and the purpose is to authorize the long-term uh ground lease for the environmental center building and grounds as councilor craig pointed out also wanted to reiterate that our city solicitor mr hanberger he did speak to city council during the july committee meeting about about the ground lease specifically we do have our outside counsel here tonight mr igor pleskov in case you have any additional questions specifically about the legal agreement although the focus here tonight really is on on the ground lease agreement it is worth noting that PES partners for environmental stewardship is making progress on the broader initiative as well the executive director of PES Ms. Diana Martin is present here this evening and wanted to give her a chance just to say a few words about the ongoing work and I think President Beke that that speaks to your opening question about how all of these pieces fit together for the community engagement ultimately the community benefit for the immediate southeast neighborhoods and for really the city and the region as a whole um i would say ultimately uh at the end of the day what what we're trying to achieve here pes is responsible for designing and constructing a world-class green building on Sunnyside and establishing environmental education programs and other similar programming to serve city residents PS has also hired a stellar consultant team and they're working closely with the city to develop a master plan for the surrounding nature preserve on Sunnyside last but not least I just wanted to say it really has been a privilege to work on this project it's truly an innovative and exemplary public private partnership the preserve and the environmental center are really intended to serve as foundational community assets for generations to come and that is largely why this 99 year long term ground lease is being put in place thank you thank you so so very much and for
highlighting all of those all the pieces that it took to get us to this time I I know I am personally extremely excited for this development on Sunnyside a long dormant area in the city development has been difficult to crack and I am appreciative that this includes an element of preserving the nature that exists there and I will get to partake in a hike by partners for environmental stewardship next month I look forward to it maybe a little bit less hot that's i chose september but i'm looking forward to getting to to see it thank you thank you counselors any additional comments from the public i'm so sorry before we do that counselor counselor royal
i missed you when i looked that way no worries thank you council president just wanted to make a comment i'm also very excited about this project i had a chance to partake on the hike maybe a few weeks ago a month ago and was very excited for someone who grew up in the southeast i'd never step foot on parts of that uh area to and there were it was very hard to believe that was in the middle of lancaster city especially uh um and where we were so it's very exciting to see what that's going to be for future generations so very excited about this thank you any additional council
comments from the public thank you tony diastra 700 block of new holland avenue i am also looking
forward to this project i think this is going to be a good investment in the environmental values our community is starting to stand behind but i also want to use this as an opportunity to kind of speak to when investment comes in one area we do have to be mindful of what occurs around it there's going to be a public hearing in september for a flexible residential development at the planning commission i want to say the date is september 17th if i forget right now but there's going to be a public hearing about potential development south of this site i believe and we need to be mindful of what occurs after this facility goes up as a community and i do trust that the stewards of this land are also going to be mindful of that but we also have to make sure we are constantly looking at ourselves and each other because this i don't know i don't have a number for this but i know a lot of money is going into this project i know that the building is going to be net negative in terms of producing carbon or at least that's the vision which is a great thing but this might be some of the biggest investment made in the community since that part of town was redlined so the pendulum can very easily swing and i would hate for this great project to end up gentrifying the community that surrounds it good evening
good evening council mayor sirachi thank you chris for the setup earlier i'm diana martin i'm the executive director of partners for environmental stewardship i'm also a proud resident of the city of lancaster it's one of the reasons i'm really passionate about this project on behalf of our organization i want to thank you for considering the ground lease agreement tonight this is a really exciting milestone for this project and just deeply grateful for the city's partnership in making it possible over the last 18 months our team has worked closely with city staff to discuss every detail of the lease agreement you've probably read it it's over 100 pages we talked extensively about what community engagement would look like on this project what it means to design a world-class green building for our community the programs that will run at the center and the ways that we'll report back to you all and to the community once were open and operating tonight's vote brings us one step closer to realizing the vision outlined in the city's 2023 comprehensive plan to transform the northern portion of sunnyside peninsula into the city's first nature preserve and to build an environmental center that reconnects our community to the conestoga river sunnyside has come up several times in this conversation so far to know sunnyside and to spend time there is to fall in love with sunnyside Sunnyside is just such a special part of our city it's shaped by the river it's steeped in history there's so much ecological potential there's 89 unique bird species we've identified out on Sunnyside it's common to see birds bats even foxes when you're out there deer it's just such a special place and this project is really about protecting that special place restoring its natural health and creating opportunities for our fellow residents to explore learn and work right in their own backyard the environmental center will serve as a hub for environmental education green job training and collaboration we have actually seven leading environmental non-profits who have signed on to either have offices there leave programming at the environmental center and the nature preserve will provide space for trails recreation and habitat restoration so i want to acknowledge the city's vision and leadership in making this a true public private partnership together not only are we expanding access to green space but also positioning lancaster as a leader in clean water environmental stewardship and sustainable waterfront development so on behalf of our board our partner organizations and many community supporters thank you for your collaboration and trust and commitment to this shared vision and we look forward to working alongside all of you to bring this project to life and anyone who's just hearing about it today i also invite you to be part of the project we're hosting public guided hikes and tours and i hope to get all of you out there i know that there's a lot of passion in this room that we can harness to make this happen so appreciate you all being here tonight too thank you any additional comments from the
public on the resolution hearing none Mr. Harris Mr. Mudd aye Mr. Royo aye Mr. Cleese aye Ms. Craig aye Ms. Diaz aye Mr. Hirsch aye President Begay aye thank you so much
next resolution on our agenda is resolution number 54 2025 Mr. Harris a resolution of the
City Council of the City of Lancaster approving a memorandum of understanding between the Lancaster county conservation district and the city of lancaster authorizing the appropriate officials of the city of lancaster to enter into such a memorandum of understanding motion to approve
second we have a motion and a second this is coming through public works councillor hirsch
thank you council president this resolution authorizes a routine update to our memorandum of understanding with the lancaster county conservation district the changes being made are primarily administrative in nature including minor word changes uh and allowing lccd to provide documents online and on its website kind of coming into the first 21st century there and decreases plan review and permitting timelines for applications for erosion and sediment control programs from 10 calendar days to five calendar days as well as an update to the lccd to reduce its inspection and inspection response timelines from 10 calendar days to eight calendar days there are no changes to the municipal responsibilities within the mou so it does not change our responsibilities in any way again this is mostly an administrative update to our memorandum of understanding with lccd thank you very much council hirsch counselors we heard
from director stephen campbell on this last evening and i just appreciate that we revisit this from time to time although we're probably required to do to do that i appreciate that we do that to look for efficiencies and i think the fact that in 2025 we're finally allowing the conservation district to have electronic files and online access is good and overdue so thank you for that any additional comments from council on the resolution from the public on the resolution
hearing none Mr. Harris Mr. Medford aye Mr. Royal aye Mr. Glees aye
Ms. Gregg aye Ms. Diaz aye Mr. Hirsch aye Mr. Bacon aye our next item on this part of the agenda is administration resolution number 55
2025 Mr. Harris a resolution of the Council of the City of Lancaster approving an easement agreement between the City of Lancaster and the Lancaster parking authority granting an easement to LPA for encouragement into the public right-of-way over North Bryn Street as more fully set forth in the easement
agreement motion to approve second you have a motion and a second councillor
Craig thank you council president I'm gonna ask that mr. Cohen come and speak on this because my computer died and my notes are in there thank you
council craig yes mr cohen will be available if there's any additional questions uh counselors we heard a presentation last evening on this easement agreement as it relates to the parking garage project on north prince street and the former offices that will be retrofitted into commercial space and the projection easement that's that's needed for above the sidewalk the clearance is noted last evening we're over eight feet by the architect and the engineer for the project i believe is who we heard from if there are any additional council comments or any additional questions mr cohen is here and available yeah i think it might be worth
mentioning too that the building sat for a long period of time over well close to nine years and now it's being revitalized to bring you know to add some beautification to the area
that's right and we also heard i have in my notes from last evening that the parking authority does already have a tenant although that those details aren't being released out of respect for wanting to ensure that they have the space to make that announcement but so thank you for that any additional council comments on the resolution from the public i'm assuming you're coming forward to speak so i'm going to give you a moment okay good evening
evening uh tony dash the 700 block new holland avenue um so i didn't realize that the parking authority was on the agenda at all when i was talking about parking earlier um but i'm just i'm not opposed to this but i do think the city needs to take a really hard look at how it's managing parking and whether or not the parking authority continues to provide it value or more specifically provide the residents the value that was kind of set up for the idea was that we're saving because we're creating operational efficiencies but what we've also done in another sense is we've created an entity which does parking management I know it has done outside of the typical eight to six but we have real residential parking concerns that yeah I want to live in a carless society too but practically we need to move through the society we're currently living in this mess that has been made and so especially now that the parking authority is getting into other ventures which are good because we're reusing space and I hope that at some point we're creating more affordable business opportunities for people as well throughout the city I think it's time for the city to reassess its relationship to the parking authority and really consider whether or not it's providing the value to the residents that it should be
thank you any additional comments from the public on the resolution
that concludes our legislative agenda this evening we'll take us to our next item on the agenda
which is our second public comment period it's open to comments on issues not previously on the agenda duration of comments again is limited to three minutes per speaker please begin with your name and block of residence for our meeting record uh brian nelson the 100
block of east lemon street and um i just want to say that we live in a great community i love that we're getting that environmental thing that's amazing right at the same time we're getting a
data center how amazing is that we're getting something that preserves our environment and
and we're destroying the environment at the same time. The priorities aren't there for me. I don't see it. And Mayor Sirachi, I want to address you directly here because you say you can't do anything, right? But as Frank pointed out, you were super, super excited about this building. So why didn't you do anything then? Why have we not tried to do, you have plenty of ideas here that you were given, right? And I understand that we're held back by red tape. And I don't think that a data center truly an awful thing for the community if done right but the thing is this was done with no public input because it was labeled as a warehouse and I'm just struggling to try to figure out where we go from here in terms of you know making sure that this doesn't happen again right and I know you guys say that you're doing your reports and I can't wait to hear them right I'll look at them and you know I will reassess my position then but I understand that the big bad bill is probably going to hurt LDH we're gonna get hurt right and we need to bring new industry to Lancaster I 100% agree with that I just don't think that this is the way to do it we're rushing into it we're just we see it as dollar signs but when in reality it's not gonna bring the jobs that you think it's gonna bring we need technology I truly believe that the tech industry is a major industry that we can have here right a data center sucks I'm just gonna put it right out there data centers destroy their communities right and we talked about potentially gentrifying a community, which I hope we don't, right, and we talked about that. But then we also talked about potentially destroying black and brown communities with data centers. So where do they go? You're gonna kick them out and then you're gonna destroy where they're gonna end up going. I just, I'm struggling to see the connect here, guys.
Thank you. Are there any additional speakers for this period? Please, good evening, thank you.
Thank you, Frank Arcolio, Old Trinity Place. I know I've been critical of the administration with respect to the data centers, but I believe in giving credit where credit is due and in order to be fair. I sat through a tremendously detailed presentation on the five-year plan for the Department of Public Works at the last council meeting, and I thought I understood that it was the very first one that had been prepared um i was very impressed with the level of i wasn't impressed with the visuals but i was very impressed with the level of detail and the thought that went into it and if that was a first attempt uh kudos to the department of public works it was a
it was very well done so thank you thank you mr arcolio and yes it is hard to make spreadsheets visibly appealing but they are interesting any additional public
comments for this Alexander King 600 block of North Shippen so kind of to play up Tony Dastro's comments I'd like to say parking management in the city is an unmitigated disaster it seems to be a sort of grassroots sort of thing which seems to be the dumbest way to plan anything I've lived in a lot of cities in Europe in North America South America and this is the only city where you can petition to have your block have parking restriction and the neighboring block doesn't so on the 600 block of North Shippen there are no parking restrictions on the 500 block of North Shippen there are parking restrictions on the 700 block of North Shippen there are parking restrictions on the 200 block of East New there are parking restrictions not the 300 block so what does this mean this means that I often see people living on one of the larger apartment on the corner of New and North Shippen Park in front of my house which is their perfect right to do because there's no parking restrictions there and then later you know I or my wife tries to come home and we can't find anywhere to park except for maybe three or four blocks away on on Park Avenue ironically and so I would like to see a just do away with the parking restrictions and then a plan set up there is no reason why there should be any parking restrictions on the 700 block in north shipping you know there's no commercial thing happening there it's too far from the hospital the only thing is that the residents of that street signed up to have those parking restrictions so that the renters on the uh large apartment buildings on the corner of new and north shipping wouldn't be able to park in front of their house uh whereas if there were no parking restrictions in in that neighborhood and there's a lot of residential neighborhoods that have a similar sort of hodgepodge thing so i would like like to see the parking authority speakers for this period good evening
good evening my name is Abby Haney I live on the 600 block of East Madison Street I didn't come here planning to speak I just wanted to listen I know I've been here talking about the data centers before and we had so many great people who showed up today to continue to advocate for action and so I really appreciate all of you who came I just had maybe one or two things that I'm still kind of wondering from the last time that I was here one of them was the community benefit agreement that I believe was mentioned that would be that'd be figured out between the city and Chris a core we I just have questions again about who is the one who's going to do the negotiating around that is it unilaterally is the community going to be involved with that because i think we really should have the ability to have a say um i also really i don't know if he's here but i also really appreciate dan weigel who came and he had a whole list of things that i believe lancaster stands up had drafted in a letter petition and i really think that those are great actionable concrete steps that the council can take full disclosure i'm here with lancaster dsa and i really appreciate the work that lancaster stands up is doing in partnership with us so i really really hope that you guys will take everything that's been said today take it in and really think about what the next steps are going to be because it's clear to me that the community doesn't want this so we'd really like for you to have some action thank you thank you are there any additional speakers for
this period hearing none we'll close the second public comment period this evening thank you to all who spoke the next item on our agenda is the report of the mayor mayor sirachi
thank you council president i i want to just echo what we have heard at the last couple council meetings and in conversations that i've been having in the community related to the data centers and just to reaffirm that we hear your concerns about water utilization air quality noise the permitting the not the permitting process itself but the zoning a determination and I am working to be able to respond to the questions and concerns additional questions that have raised about where the power is coming from and and the entirety of like the environmental impact and have begun to have conversations about an environmental impact report that would address all of these things I also just want to be mindful of again the the questions about power and power usage and electricity rates and reliability of the grid are not things that i'm going to be able to answer because that is not in my wheelhouse i have been trying to get those questions answered and will continue to try to get those questions answered by other entities in pennsylvania most especially ppl and i'm trying to understand what i can about how all of that works and so i'm going to stop with my comments there i just want to say i hear you and i believe that council also hears you i know that my our administration the people that are working on your behalf every day hear you and we are working to run down the information that is needed to answer the questions that have been raised not only by the people in this room but by others as well the second thing that i want to mention is about residential parking permits since that's been the topic of conversation tonight to say that that is really in the purview of the traffic commission and the traffic commission engaged a team to begin to address residential parking across the city and they are having meetings in our neighborhoods to address residential parking in those communities i agree with you alex that is crazy that um we have these residential parking permit blocks that some of them were approved decades ago when there was a commercial use and now there's no commercial use and there's no way to like take them off the rolls or to revisit that that was one of the things that was highlighted in the in the recommendations that the traffic commission i believe is working to advance so there's a lot more that's happening related to the residential parking it is a huge challenge because there are more cars in the city than the city was ever intended to have um the third thing that i want to take us back to is something that was really great this morning and this is really um council to take you back to when we were able to allocate 10 million dollars to affordable housing and this morning i was able to attend a ribbon cutting for the manor street uh the manor youth house located on manor street as you might imagine this project will provide safe stable housing for up to nine young adults ages 18 to 25 who are homeless or transitioning out of foster care are at risk of homelessness they will have on-site support services and and this project is being led by community basics as well as the valley youth house which is a regional leader in youth support services to bring this project to life and I just thought you should know that the investments that council made are coming to fruition I'm gonna have more to say about the ARPA housing investments in the coming weeks but this morning was a very sweet event to participate in and to see that this is filling a really critical need in our community for young people who are aging out of foster care with that i conclude my report thank you very much mayor sirachi i appreciate the
update on the man of youth house um these projects take a long time we make these investments we did so a couple years ago so it's nice to get the update in it it's really happening so i appreciate that the next item on the agenda is a report of the president of council i did speak earlier and with back-to-back meetings i'm beginning to lose my voice so i'm going to uh forego my report at this time uh will then take us to council comments are there any council comments this evening
councilor ahmed thank you council president and i do want to thank all of the members of the community who have come out and spoken at the past several meetings i did request a report on the current status of the data center and what council's options are moving forward and i do look forward to that report thank you that concludes my comments thank you very much
counselor med any additional council comments this evening hearing none and having reached the conclusion of our agenda I'll hear motion to adjourn there's a motion and a second all in favor aye we're adjourned thank you